Guide to the Roberta Wood Papers TAM.626
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Roberta Wood Papers
1969-2024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wood, Roberta
TAM.626
2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
Roberta Wood (1949-) has served as Secretary Treasurer of the Communist Party since 2007. A lifelong rank and file union activist, Roberta co-founded the steelworker women's caucus in the in the Chicago/Gary district of the Steelworkers union. In 1976 she was elected the first female member of USWA Local 65's Executive Board. Following the closing of US Steel's South Works mill, Roberta worked until retirement as an electrical instrumentation mechanic in a municipal sewage treament facility. She served several years as labor editor of the People's Weekly World, forerunner to the People's World. The Roberta Wood Papers consists of materials collected by Wood over the course of her decades of labor organizing and political activism. Much of the collection documents Wood's early communist activism, with particular emphasis on her work with the Young Workers Liberation League (YWLL). Included in her YWLL records are fliers, publications, organizing documents, and meeting notes and minutes. This collection also includes Wood's notes from a party-related political education program/workers school; documentation from Wood's involvement in the Coalition of Labor Union Women; documents from her time organizing with the CPUSA's Southern California District; and notes and slides from the World Assembly of Builders of Peace Meeting in Warsaw, Poland in 1977; as well as documents given to her by Al Hanover and leftist ephemera and publications. Materials also include financial statements, publicity, and planning materials from the Labor Education Fund's tribute for Florence Reece and the Ernesto De Maio Tribute Committee's tribute for Ernie De Maio, both in the 1970s. The collection also contains an oral history with Wood conducted in 2012, and biographies of numerous leaders in the labor, civil rights, and peace movements, collected for the Unity Center's (likely unpublished) Honor Roll and Golden Book of the Working Class.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Roberta Wood in 2012; additional materials were donated in 2014, December 2023, and March 2025. The accession number related to these gifts are 2012.082, 2024.011, and 2025.052.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Roberta Wood (1949-) has served as Secretary Treasurer of the Communist Party since 2007. A lifelong rank and file union activist, Roberta co-founded the steelworker women's caucus in the in the Chicago/Gary district of the Steelworkers union. In 1976 she was elected the first female member of USWA Local 65's Executive Board. Following the closing of US Steel's South Works mill, Roberta worked until retirement as an electrical instrumentation mechanic in a municipal sewage treament facility. She served several years as labor editor of the People's Weekly World, forerunner to the People's World.
Source: Communist Party USA. "Roberta Wood." http://www.cpusa.org/new-biography-2 (accessed January 30, 2024).
Related Materials
Researchers interested in Roberta Wood may also wish to consult the following collections at the Tamiment Library:
Daily Worker and Daily World Photographs Collection (PHOTOS 223)
Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132)
Scope and Contents
The Roberta Wood Papers consists of materials collected by Wood over the course of her decades of labor organizing and political activism. Much of the collection documents Wood's early communist activism, with particular emphasis on her work with the Young Workers Liberation League (YWLL). Included in her YWLL records are fliers, publications, organizing documents, and meeting notes and minutes. This collection also includes Wood's notes from a party-related political education program/workers school; documentation from Wood's involvement in the Coalition of Labor Union Women; documents from her time organizing with the CPUSA's Southern California District; and notes and slides from the World Assembly of Builders of Peace Meeting in Warsaw, Poland in 1977; as well as documents given to her by Al Hanover and leftist ephemera and publications. Materials also include financial statements, publicity, and planning materials from the Labor Education Fund's tribute for Florence Reece and the Ernesto De Maio Tribute Committee's tribute for Ernie De Maio, both in the 1970s. The collection also contains an oral history with Wood conducted in 2012, and biographies of numerous leaders in the labor, civil rights, and peace movements, collected for the Unity Center's (likely unpublished) Honor Roll and Golden Book of the Working Class.
Labor leaders -- United States.; Peace movements; Women communists -- United States.; Communism.; Youth movements -- United States.; Wood, Roberta; Reece, Florence, 1900-1986; De Maio, Ernest; Young Workers Liberation League; United Steelworkers of America
- Pete Seeger--Florence Reece, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ernie De Maio Tribute, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- World Assembly of Builders of Peace, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Biographies--Honor Roll--Founders, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
- Roberta Wood Oral History Interview, March 23, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- [Copenhagen Appeal Notes], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Party Political Education Notes, late 1970s (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Young Workers Liberation League -- Publications, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Young Workers Liberation League -- Organizing Documents and Publications, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Young Workers Liberation League -- Organizing Documents and Fliers, 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Young Workers Liberation League -- Binder 1, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Young Workers Liberation League -- Binder 2, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- CPUSA -- Southern California District, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Left Publications and Fliers, 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Documents from Al Hanover; Ficher Body Plant UAW, 1969-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Peggy Dennis, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Kransdorf, Herb, 1997-2018 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Steelworkers -- Clippings and Newsletters, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Rank-and-File -- Publications, Elections, 1975-2024 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
- Sadlowski, Ed -- Election, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- National Steelworkers Rank-and-File, 1971-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- World Youth Festival, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Labor-related Ephemera, 1948-2010 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- National Steel Commission, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Files Found in CPUSA Building, 1973-1995 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
- Deceased CPUSA Members -- Ishmael Flory; (Tom) Thomas Meyerscough; Tim Wheeler, 1971-2012 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Notebook from LA Party Meetings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)